# Ryan Tremarco

## Senior Software Engineer

ryantremarco@hotmail.co.uk

tremarco.dev

የጌ github.com/ryantremarco

## Experience

### **Benefex**

**Senior Backend Engineer**: May 2023 - September 2024, Remote / Southampton Backend Engineer: January 2023 - April 2024, Remote / Southampton

- Leading the development of a Microsoft Teams application that integrates with core products and APIs for custom notification delivery and product interaction
- Development of event-driven Go microservices, deployed to GCP kubernetes clusters via CircleCl and Terraform
- Owned and implemented a centralised notifications system for the core product suite, enabling email, web, mobile, and now Microsoft Teams push notifications to users from any of our backend services
- Led the refactoring and replacement of ageing parts of the service landscape while maintaining service contracts for compatibility and enabling new workflows such as customer globalisation (an average revenue increase of 33% per customer)
- Improved backend chapter's workflow by creating proposals for and implementing packages for standard error structures, event outboxing, and API clients

#### **VISFO**

Backend Engineer: July 2021 - January 2023, Remote / Brighouse

- Technical ownership of 'Curator' project to replace and then enhance process for progressing and providing feedback on employee-submitted work
- Development of Golang API microservices following MVC patterns hosted on GCP
- Implementing gateway aggregation of microservices using GraphQL to make complex calls across microservices and preventing over fetching
- Implementing dataloader techniques with GraphQL resolvers to aggregate database and network calls into batches and significantly reduce network load
- Implementation and management of general GCP infrastructure including IAM and Role Management performed via terraform
- Implementation and management of ETL/ELT pipelines using a mixture of in-house python scripting, Airbyte pipelines, and DBT transformations
- Advocate for implementing Agile practices where there were no official ways-of-working and maintaining a guiding role at ceremonies

### Her Majesty's Government

Full Stack Engineer: September 2017 - July 2021, Manchester

- Development of Java REST microservices using Spring MVC and Eureka
- Development of Node JS APIs using a custom fork of PKI auth-enabled Express
- Deploying services to OpenShift using S2I to AWS EKS
- Development of React apps; hands-on UX/UI using customer-centric workshops
- Maintenance and expansion of data pipelines built in Apache Camel
- Contribution to internal-source frameworks used by but not managed by own project team over developing workarounds to benefit the wider organisation

## **About Me**

Hello! I'm a Software Engineer with experience working across the full stack of web development and I have a particular liking to backend API development.

I do my best to bring a level of pragmatism to the projects that I am a part of. I understand and make as much use of best practice as possible, but I also know that chasing perfection in our work is a never-ending task. Knowing where to stop, or where best to break a convention in order to deliver projects is as great a part of being an Engineer as system design or implementation in my opinion.

Communication is also something that is very important to me and I have worked hard to improve over the years. I like to share information as much as possible with colleagues to help reduce single-point-of-failure risks and siloing within teams. To this end I have tried to make it a habit to organise pairing / mobbing / learning / lightning talk sessions with team members in order to share knowledge and help upskill others in areas that I am a local expert in.

At home I like to experiment with tech that I don't get to use day-to-day like Rust and Haskell. I have found that I personally learn best by doing, so I like to take part in programming events such as Advent of Code in order to help with this. More recently I've been dabbling in game development via game jams and I'm particularly enjoying using Godot's node system.

Outside of tech, my interests generally lean towards hobbies like video games, Warhammer, tabletop RPGs like Mothership and D&D, and boardgames. I also dabble in language learning and have been teaching myself Japanese for a few years now; I'm hoping to pick up some Italian in the future too.

## **Skills**

#### Languages:

- Go
- Java + Spring
- JavaScript + React
- Bash
- Rust

## **Tooling:**

- Linux / WSL2
- Git
- Grafana + Prometheus
- PostgreSQL
- MongoDB
- MariaDB
- Mariab
- Neo4j

### Infrastructure:

- GCP
- OpenShift
- AWS
- Terraform

## **Education**

University of Roehampton / BSc Digital and Technology Solutions (1st)

SEPTEMBER 2017 - JANUARY 2021

While working at HMG, I was fortunate enough to be sponsored to complete my first-class degree with honours. The work for this was completed in my own time alongside full-time software projects.